{"tossups": [{"question": "After the founder of this group assassinated Constantine Manciu, the jury at his trial was obviously biased in his favor to the point of wearing swastikas at the trial. When this group was banned by the Vaida-Voevod government, it retaliated by assassinating Prime Minister Ion Duca at the Sinaia railway station. In 1935, this party changed its name to the \u201cEverything for the Country\u201d Party. Horia Sima led this group, which was alternately named the Legion of the Archangel Michael. Ion Antonescu shut down, for the point, what fascist movement in Romania?", "answer": "<b> Iron Guard</b> (accept<b> Totul Pentra Tara</b>; accept<b> Legionaires\u2019</b> Movement; accept<b> Legion of the Archangel Michael</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A female warrior in this country was quoted as saying, \u201cI\u2019d like to ride storms, kill sharks in the open sea.\u201d In this country, a \u201cpole-and-tide\u201d stratagem was employed to destroy enemy ships because when the tide ebbed, the ships would be penetrated by the poles. During a 1288 Mongol invasion of this country, Omar Khan was defeated at the Battle of Bach Dang River. The first Chinese domination of this nation was resisted by Trac and Nhi, two of the Trung sisters. Under Tran Hung Dao, this country repelled three major invasions. For the point, name this country where the Nguyen Dynasty established a capital at Thang Long in what is now Hanoi.", "answer": "<b> Vietnam</b> (or<b> Dai Viet</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This artist painted an ornate golden head on a sword hilt resting in the foreground in front of a square pillar decorated with this artist\u2019s signature while a woman raises a hammer above a sleeping Canaanite. This painter of<em> Jael and Sisera</em> referred to Cesare Ripa\u2019s<em> Iconologia</em> for a painting in which this artist wears a small mask on a chain and leans on a pigment grinding stone as a<em> Self-Portrait as the Allegory of</em> <em>Painting</em>. In another painting, she depicted two women struggling to kill a man who resembles this artist\u2019s rapist. For the point, name this Italian Baroque painter of<em> Judith Slaying Holofernes</em>.", "answer": "Artemisia<b> Gentileschi</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In the 14th century in what is now this state, hundreds of villagers of the Initial Coalescent people were killed in the Crow Creek massacre. In 1890, Samuel Whitside and James Forsyth led an attack on Spotted Elk\u2019s men in this state; the next day, after a deaf man named Black Coyote didn\u2019t give up his rifle, the 7th Cavalry carried out the Wounded Knee Massacre. The Pine Ridge Reservation is in, for the point, what US state where an 1870s gold rush led to attacks on the Sioux in the Black Hills?", "answer": "<b> South Dakota</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A Trast\u00b4amara queen with this name lost control of Castille via the Treaty of Alc\u00b4acovas; that woman\u2019s husband lost a battle that was seen as retribution for Aljubarrota, the Battle of Toro. Another queen with this name was the mother of Holy Roman Emperor Ferdinand I and refused to bury her husband, Philip the Handsome, after his death in 1506. Archbishop Cisneros served as regent to a daughter of Isabella I with this name. For the point, give this name shared by a decidedly insane queen of Castille.", "answer": "<b> Joanna</b> (accept<b> Joanna</b> La Betraneja; accept<b> Joanna</b> the Mad or<b> Juana</b> la Loca)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Li Shimin seized power in this dynasty during the Xuanwu Gate Incident. One of the Four Beauties of China, Yang Guifei, was blamed for a rebellion faced by this dynasty. This dynasty\u2019s Xuanzong Emperor faced the rival Yan Dynasty in the An Lushan Rebellion, and it beat the Abbasids at the Battle of the Talas River. The Golden Age of Chinese Poetry, including the works of poet Li Bai, was during, for the point, what dynasty whose rulers included Empress Wu Zetian and which preceded the Song dynasty?", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A member of this family wrote a pamphlet in the aftermath of the Denmark Vesey conspiracy claiming that teaching slaves literacy was extremely dangerous. Another member of this family signed a loyalty oath to Britain in an attempt to protect Snee Farm. At Wappoo Plantation, a woman who married into this family introduced indigo to the South. A member of this family led the American delegation in the XYZ Affair as John Adams\u2019 Vice President. Eliza Lucas married into, for the point, what South Carolina family that included Charles Cotesworth?", "answer": "<b> Pinckney</b> family", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In an opera set in this country, the monk Athanael tries to convince the title courtesan to follow him to find God; that 1894 opera features a \u201cMeditation\u201d for solo violin and was composed by Jules Massenet. Costuming for the premiere of an opera set in this country was delayed due to the Franco-Prussian War; that opera uses 12 elephants in a \u201ctriumphal march.\u201d A princess is entombed with her lover Radames in, for the point, what country where the Khedivial Opera House premiered Verdi\u2019s<em> Aida</em> in Cairo?", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "This battle may have been decided after Adeimantus swapped sides. Evagoras, the king of Cyprus, helped shelter survivors fleeing from this battle. Xenophon claims that \u201cno one slept\u201d after news of this battle arrived via the ship<em> Paralus</em>. This battle\u2019s result cut off trade routes to the harbor at Piraeus, starving defenders and citizens inside the Long Walls. The Thirty Tyrants were installed following, for the point, what victory for Lysander\u2019s Spartans, the last major battle of the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Aegospotami</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man, who narrowly avoided accepting free passage on the<em> Titanic</em> by leaving on the<em> Lusitania</em> a few days earlier, met with Harold Bride and testified about the use of his invention during the disaster. This prominent fascist had his personal yacht,<em> Elettra</em>, outfitted into a warship after his death by the occupying Nazis. The message \u201cAre you ready?\u201d was sent by this man in 1897 using Morse code. The first transatlantic cable line was set up by, for the point, what co-winner of the 1909 Nobel Prize in Physics, an Italian inventor of radio?", "answer": "Guglielmo<b> Marconi</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s followers were called the \u201cfuzzy wuzzies\u201d after the elaborately styled hair of the Hadendoa tribe. After studying with Muhammad Sharif, this man began taking apprentices of his own at Aba Island. This man drew the ire of authorities after William Hicks\u201d column was ambushed by this man\u2019s dervishes. Abdallahi wad Torshayn succeeded this man after a fatal bout of typhus. This man managed to defeat Charles Gordon, but his cause eventually fell apart at the Battle of Omdurman. For the point, identify this 19th century messianic figure who led a revolt against the British in Sudan.", "answer": "<b> Muhammad Ahmad</b> bin Abd Allah (accept the<b> Mahdi</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this first prime minister of Great Britain.", "answer": "Sir Robert<b> Walpole</b>, 1st Earl of<b> Orford</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A speech given in the aftermath of this event stated that its victim was a \u201cStradivarius, whose notes rose in competition with jealous drums.\u201d Gerald L. K. Smith posited that this event allowed the owner of the Roosevelt Hotel to steal funds raised for a 1936 presidential campaign. The perpetrator of this event, the son-in-law of judge Benjamin Pavy, was shot dozens of times by bodyguards. One of several conflicting sources holds that this event included the dying lament \u201cI have so much to do.\u201d On September 8, 1935, Carl Weiss carried out, for the point, what fatal attack on a Louisiana politician nicknamed Kingfish?", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> shooting</b>, etc.) of Huey P.<b> Long</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In Article 40 of a document drafted by this ruler, he called for direct taxes of 300 francs on members of an electoral college. This man married a woman who never used perfume or brushed her teeth, Marie Jos\u00b4ephine of Savoy. The Chamber of Deputies and the Chamber of Peers were created as part of a bicameral legislature this man outlined in the Charter of 1814. This man was next in line to the throne after his nephew died at age 10, and was made king as part of the Bourbon Restoration. For the point, name this brother of Louis XVI who served as king of France before and after Napoleon\u2019s Hundred Days.", "answer": "<b> Louis XVIII</b> [18] of France (accept<b> Louis the Desired</b>; prompt on \u201cLouis\u201d) Page 3", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A man in this position maintained a group of advisors called the \u201cBlack Kitchen Cabinet,\u201d including future African-American Cabinet member Robert Weaver. A man in this Cabinet position reportedly originated the quote \u201cI drink your milkshake.\u201d The longest-serving person to hold this position was Harold Ickes, who helped black singer Marian Anderson perform at the Lincoln Memorial. During the Harding presidency, Albert B. Fall held this position and during the Teapot Dome scandal, took bribes to allow oil companies to drill at government-owned reserves. For the point, name this Cabinet position which manages the USA\u2019s natural resources.", "answer": "Secretary of the<b> Interior</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A vault in this location held over $6 million when Jimmy Burke\u2019s crew robbed it in December 1978, a robbery that became part of the plot of Martin Scorsese\u2019s film<em> Goodfellas</em>. Viktor Navorski, played by Tom Hanks, is trapped in this location in Steven Spielberg\u2019s<em> The Terminal</em> when US customs stops recognizing the fictional country of Krakozhia. This facility in the neighborhood of Jamaica in Queens is southeast of a smaller facility named for Mayor Fiorella La Guardia. For the point, name this primary international airport in New York that was renamed for an assassinated president in 1963.", "answer": "John F.<b> Kennedy</b> International Airport (accept<b> JFK</b> Airport; accept additional information, like \u201cNew York-<b>JFK</b>;\u201d accept<b> Idlewild</b> Airport; do not accept or prompt on partial answers like \u201cNew York Airport\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A myth in this country states that a candidate repeatedly asked a Conservative \u201cHow did you get this land?\u201d until he got the reply \u201cWe took it from the natives.\u201d A presidential candidate in this country was targeted in Operation Pantomime and eventually killed by Juan Roa Sierra. Alberto Lleras Camargo was the first Liberal leader to take power in this country\u2019s power sharing agreement from 1958 to 1974, the National Front. The death of Jorge Eli\u00b4ecer Gait\u00b4an sparked unrest in this nation leading to a civil war called \u201cLa Violencia.\u201d For the point, name this South American country where Gait\u00b4an\u2019s assassination provoked riots in Bogota.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Colombia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man may have advocated for a preemptive nuclear attack on the Soviet Union in a speech at Westminster School. This man and Albert Einstein co-name a manifesto that called for the first Pugwash Conference. This man attempted to develop a series of sets and axioms from which all mathematics could be derived in a work co-written with Alfred North Whitehead. For the point, name this 20th century mathematician and philosopher who wrote<em> Principia Mathematica</em>.", "answer": "Bertrand<b> Russell</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Harry Laughlin designed the \u201cModel Law\u201d on which this case depended. Dr. Sidney Priddy filed a petition that led to this court case, which concerned Arthur Estabrook\u2019s analysis of Vivian Alice Elaine Dobbs as \u201cbackward.\u201d A \u201cpromiscuous\u201d mother was the plaintiff in this case, in which an 8-1 majority upheld a Virginia law that was repealed in 1974. Oliver Wendell Holmes declared that \u201cThree generations of imbeciles are enough\u201d in, for the point, what 1927 Supreme Court decision that promoted eugenics by allowing forced sterilization of the mentally disabled?", "answer": "<b> Buck</b> v.<b> Bell</b> (accept either or both underlined names) Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 935, the Fatimid Caliphate\u2019s navy sacked this city, whose leaders included a First Crusade member with the sobriquet \u201cmallet head.\u201d The Bank of Saint George was founded in this city, which helped France win the Barbary Crusade against Mahdia. Sailors often wore \u201cBlue Jean\u201d cloth from this city, which lost the War of Chioggia. This city, which controlled Gazaria and Caffa on the Black Sea coast helped win the Battle of Lepanto under Andrea Dorea. Christopher Columbus hailed from, for the point, what maritime Italian rival of Venice?", "answer": "<b> Genoa</b> (accept<b> Genova</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A history of this group is maintained in the Old Charges, and the Regius Poem documents how King Aethelstan created their fifteen articles. Prince Hall created an African American offshoot of this group. L\u00b4eo Taxil mocked this group and the Catholic Church in a hoax. The disappearance of William Morgan inspired a political party opposed to this group. Members of this organization form Lodges and believe in a Supreme Being. The ranks of Apprentice and Journeyman form part of, for the point, what fraternal organization named for stonecraft masters?", "answer": "<b> Mason</b>s (accept<b> Freemason</b>s; accept word forms like (Free)<b>masonry</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician\u2019s inability to communicate with China\u2019s U.N. delegation led to the selection of Kurt Waldheim as Secretary-General in 1971. This man, the first to officially serve as Acting President, bragged that his campaign was full of the \u201cBig Mo\u201d in an election in which he decried his opponent\u2019s policies as\u201cvoodoo economics.\u201d This president extolled volunteerism in his \u201cthousand points of light\u201d speech. For the point, name this Republican president whose son later served as the 43rd US president.", "answer": "George<b> H</b>erbert<b> W</b>alker<b> Bush</b> (accept<b> Bush the Elder</b>,<b> Bush</b> the<b> 41</b>st; prompt on (George) Bush; do not accept \u201cGeorge Walker Bush\u201d or other references to his son; do not accept George Bush Sr.) Page 5", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1920, this country faced the Pitchfork Uprising when peasants refused to give up their food. A revolt in this country\u2019s \u201cCentral Agricultural Zone\u201d was described as the \u201cJacquerie of 1905.\u201d A rebel in this country took the cathedral at Yaitsk while disguised as a pilgrim but failed to take Simbrisk. Stenka Razin and Kondraty Bulavin led revolts in this country, where Yemelyan Pugachev\u2019s cossacks were crushed in the 1770s. For the point, name this country where serfs finally gained emancipation under Alexander II.", "answer": "<b> Russia</b>n Empire (do not accept Soviet Union)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Jeremiah Haralson and James Rapier, two black representatives from this state, split the Republican vote and lost to Charles Shelley in a gerrymandered 1876 election. A Civil War camp in this state nicknamed \u201cCastle Morgan\u201d was located in its former capital of Cahaba. This state\u2019s peonage laws were overturned in a 1911 13th Amendment case,<em> Bailey v.</em> this state. This state\u2019s soldiers were known as\u201cYellowhammers\u201d during the Civil War. After the War of 1812, this state\u2019s \u201cFever\u201d was a land grab for fertile \u201cBlack Belt\u201d soil. For the point, name this Southern state where the Confederate blockade was completed at the Battle of Mobile Bay.", "answer": "<b> Alabama</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Educational methods that were originally developed for people living in this region are described in Paulo Freire\u2019s book<em> Pedagogy of the Oppressed</em>. Patrick Tierny accused James Neel and Napoleon Chagnon of performing unethical research on people in this region in the book<em> Darkness in El Dorado</em>. Daniel Everett studied a tribe from this region who speak a language that lacks words for specific numbers. The Yanomami and Pirah\u02dca live in, for the point, what rainforest in South America?", "answer": "<b> Amazon</b> rainforest (accept<b> Amazon</b> River basin or similar answers; prompt on South America; prompt on Brazil)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "Three shootings in this city, including the 2006 Dawson College shooting, were controversially linked by Jan Wong\u2019s article \u201cGet under the desk,\u201d in which Wong described the history of the phrase \u201cpure wool.\u201d At another university in this city, women were separated from men and deliberately executed at the \u00b4Ecole Polytechnique. In 1970, the \u201cLiberation Cell\u201d kidnapped James Cross and killed James Laporte in, for the point, what city where much of the terror of the October Crisis was committed by Quebecois separatists?", "answer": "<b> Montreal</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The \u201cworld\u2019s first industrial suburb\u201d, Ancoats, was built in this city. The \u201cArdwick Bridge\u201d conspiracy ended this city\u2019s Blanket March to protest against the regent. Richard Arkwright\u2019s experimentation with cotton mills in this city led to it being known as \u201cCottonopolis\u201d. Henry Hunt addressed a crown in a field in this city, but its Yeomanry cut down many people in the Peterloo Massacre. The first steam railway in the world connected this city with Liverpool. For the point, name this Lancashire city that was home to many Industrial Revolution-era mills and is now home to namesake United and City soccer teams.", "answer": "<b> Manchester</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A Confederate general with this surname was a priest who named four of his guns after the gospel writers; that man was nicknamed \u201cParson.\u201d Another man with this surname ran on George McClellan\u2019s ticket as the Democratic Party\u2019s vice-presidential candidate in 1864. That man, nicknamed \u201cGentleman George,\u201d names and helped write a bill supported by the Half-Breeds that was finally passed by lame duck Republicans in early 1883 after the assassination of James Garfield. For the point, give this surname of the namesake of a Civil Service Reform Act.", "answer": "<b> Pendleton</b> (accept William<b> Pendleton</b>; accept George<b> Pendleton</b>; accept<b> Pendleton</b> (Civil Service Reform) Act) Page 7", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s unofficial political party, the Frateschi, successfully removed the longstanding punishment of exile. Piero the Unfortunate was succeeded by this man after he successfully begged Charles VIII of France to spare his city. This man was supported by the Piagnoni, but he fell from power after losing a challenge to walk through fire. Sandro Botticelli may have burned some of his own paintings on the orders of this man. The Medici family were briefly expelled by, for the point, what Dominican friar who controlled Florence in the late 15th century and ordered the Bonfire of the Vanities?", "answer": "Girolamo<b> Savonarola</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A leader of this dynasty had a \u201cLake of Wine and Forest of Meat\u201d and was married to a woman portrayed as a fox spirit, Daji. A myth stated that this dynasty was founded after Jiandi swallowed a black bird\u2019s egg and gave birth to Xie. King Wu defeated this dynasty with Jiang Ziya\u2019s help. The ruins of Yinxu represent the last capital of this dynasty, which fell at the Battle of Muye. Archaeologists have studied ox scapulae and turtle shells to learn about writing and divination during, for the point, what Chinese dynasty that preceded the semi-mythical Xia and was succeeded by the Zhou?", "answer": "<b> Shang</b> Dynasty (accept<b> Yin</b> Dynasty before \u201cYinxu\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle finally ended when the losing side managed to retreat behind the Narew River at Osovets. This battle coincided with an uprising by the Home Army in Vilnius during Operation Ostra Bama. During this battle, the tactic of<em> maskirovka</em> was used to deceive the losing side into defending Lvov. The Lublin-Brest Offensive began near the end of this battle as one side gained a foothold in Eastern Poland. A prince who fought in the Napoleonic Wars names, for the point, what 1944 battle in which the Soviet Union destroyed Germany\u2019s Army Group Centre?", "answer": "Operation<b> Bagration</b> (accept descriptions of the Soviet Union\u2019s strategic offensive operation in<b> Belorussia</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1978, Ali Abdallah Saleh became president of part of this country, which unified in 1990. The 2000 USS<em> Cole</em> bombing took place in, for the point, what country on the Arabian Peninsula where the British faced the Aden Emergency?", "answer": "<b> Yemen</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This composer showed Henri Akoka the sketches for what would become his \u201cAbyss of the Birds.\u201dThis composer used unconventional instruments like the Proven\u00b8cal tabor and ondes Martenot in a symphony premiered by Leonard Bernstein in 1949. A guard acquired three instruments for the premiere of a piece by this composer that opens with a \u201cCrystal Liturgy\u201d section and ends with a \u201cPraise to the immortality of Jesus;\u201d that piece by this composer was written while in a POW camp in Gorlitz, Germany. For the point, name this composer of the<em> Turangalila-Symphonie</em> and the<em> Quartet for the End of Time</em>.", "answer": "Olivier<b> Messiaen</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Evidence produced during this event included a photograph of Robert Stevens and the central figure that was allegedly doctored to remove Frank Carr and Colonel Jack Bradley. A letter supposedly written by J. Edgar Hoover to Herbert Brownell Jr. was procured during this event, in which one man asked for a list of 130 people \u201cbefore the sun goes down.\u201d Fred Fisher\u2019s membership in the National Lawyers Guild, the \u201clegal bulwark of the Communist Party,\u201d was attacked during this event, which infuriated Joseph Welch. Karl Mundt chaired, for the point, what series of Senate hearings in 1954 involving a branch of the armed forces in which a Wisconsin senator was asked \u201chave you left no sense of decency?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Army-McCarthy</b> hearings (accept descriptions related to Senate hearings concerning the US<b> Army</b> and Joseph<b> McCarthy</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s rule, the poor<em> hyperakrioi</em> were brought into politics for the first time as the \u201chill dweller\u201d party. This man\u2019s dynasty began to collapse after one of his sons was assassinated by Harmodius and Aristogeiton in 514 BC. This man controversially rode into the city in a golden chariot with a woman dressed as Athena to end his first of two stints in exile. The Panathenaic Games were established during the reign of, for the point, what father of Hippias and Hipparchus who led Athens as tyrant on three separate occasions in the six century BC?", "answer": "<b> Pisistratus</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This city was the subject of an early graph theory problem proposed by Leonhard Euler [oy-ler] dealing with seven of its bridges. Following World War II, this city was given to the USSR, and it remains an exclave of Russia. For the point, name this East Prussian city known today as Kaliningrad.", "answer": "<b> Konigsb\u00a8erg</b> (prompt on Kaliningrad)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This dynasty\u2019s coins are sorted into the Garuda, lion, and border legend varieties. The Buddhist monk Fa Xian wrote an account of this dynasty during a visit in the reign of King Vikramaditya. This dynasty consolidated its rule by conquering the Oxus valley, according to Kalidasa. The Iron Pillar is a lasting monument of this dynasty, which eventually fell to attacks from the White Huns. Samudra and Chandra were responsible for the early expansion of, for the point, what dynasty that was considered to be the \u201cGolden Age\u201d of India from the 4th to 6th centuries AD?", "answer": "<b> Gupta</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In a painting by this artist set at Gennevilliers, a figure in a blue coat and straw hat carries a bag along a narrow path. In another painting, this artist\u2019s mother and sister sit together, wearing contrasting white and black dresses and reading. This artist painted<em> In the Wheat</em> en plein air, and was credited with maintaining \u201cfeminine grace\u201d among \u201cfive or six lunatics\u201d in an 1874 review of the first Impressionist exhibition. For the point, name this French painter who created<em> Woman and Child on a Balcony</em> and<em> The</em> <em>Cradle</em>.", "answer": "Berthe Marie Pauline<b> Morisot</b> Page 10", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "After a European emissary went upstream to these people\u2019s capital of Orapakes, the native women tortured Captain John Ratcliffe and the men killed the rest. A chief of these people was shot in the back by a guard after being captured by William Berkeley. Chief Opchanacanough [ope-uh-CHANK-an-oh] led these people on surprise raids in 1622, killing one quarter of Jamestown\u2019s population. Englishman John Smith was captured by, for the point, what Virginian Native American tribe that included the princess Pocahontas?", "answer": "<b> Powhatan</b>s (accept<b> Powhatan</b> Confederacy; prompt on Algonquins)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city was the site of an early Victorian skyscraper, the APA building, which briefly claimed to be the world\u2019s tallest building. This city\u2019s \u201cCanvas Town\u201d tent camp served new migrants during an 1851 gold rush. Batman\u2019s Treaty was a purchase agreement for this city\u2019s land around Port Phillip Bay on the Yarra River. The 1956 Summer Olympics were held in this city, which served as seat of government until Canberra took over in 1927. For the point, name this city in the state of Victoria, the second-largest Australian city after Sydney.", "answer": "<b> Melbourne</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "An early church theologian who worked in this city moved to Caesarea after Demetrius failed to ordain him. Arian was a priest in this city\u2019s Baucalis district, where St. Mark was reportedly martyred. This city, where Origen first taught, was also the site of an institution located in the Mouseion that included researchers like Eratosthenes, who calculated the Earth\u2019s circumference. An angry mob in this city killed the mathematician Hypatia. Ptolemy II founded a large library in, for the point, what Egyptian city named for a \u201cGreat\u201d Macedonian leader?", "answer": "<b> Alexandria</b>, Egypt", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "During the rule of a monarch with this name, his minister Luis de Haro lost the Battle of the Lines of Elvas. The Count-Duke of Olivares and the Duke of Lerma served as prime ministers for two monarchs with this name. Another monarch with this name led a country that faced five bankruptcies in the late 1500s and annexed Portugal. While opposing Elizabeth I, a king of this name sent the Spanish Armada. Several Kings of Spain had, for the point, what name held by the son of Hapsburg king Charles V?", "answer": "<b> Philip</b> (accept<b> Philip</b> IV,<b> Philip</b> III or<b> Philip</b> II of Spain)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This city was seized by the Chinese pirate Limahong in 1574 and captured again in 1762 by British commander William Draper during the Seven Years\u201d War. Fighting in this city led to the liberation of the Santo Tomas Internment Camp while Tomoyuki Yamashita carried out a massacre of many civillians. During World War II, this city\u2019s walled Intramuros was largely shelled into rubble. In 1942, American forces held out in this city\u2019s bay on Corregidor Island. For the point, name this city where, in 1898, Admiral Patricio Montijo lost a key battle in the Spanish-American War to George Dewey.", "answer": "<b> Manila</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1980, police in this state altered a crime scene after beating Arthur McDuffie to death. In this state, the Carrier family defended their house against the KKK in Rosewood. A lodge owner in this state threw hydrochloric acid into a pool full of black protesters during a movement led by Robert Hayling. In 2000, Border Patrol agents stormed a house in this state to secure Elian Gonzalez, a six-year-old boy who was returned to his father in Cuba. For the point, name this state, the site of the Saint Augustine civil rights movement and the 1980 Miami riots.", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This speech was leaked to the New York Times after a copy of it was acquired by Wiktor Grajewski. A story about a world leader shaking his finger to cause Tito to fall is recounted in this speech. This speech declared there was no \u201caffair of the doctor plotters\u201d and supposedly caused heart attacks when it was first delivered to the 20th Congress of the Soviet Union. \u201cOn the Cult of Personality and Its Consequences\u201d is the official title of, for the point, what Nikita Khrushchev speech criticizing Joseph Stalin?", "answer": "Khrushchev\u2019s<b> Secret Speech</b> (accept<b> On the Cult of Personality</b> and its Consequences", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A battle in this war opened with ground attacks on the Orphan Hills. A woodcut made as propaganda during this war shows a leader waking from a nightmare of his injured troops returning home. During this war, an admiral raised the Z-flag and \u201ccrossed the T\u201d of the enemy line of ships. A replacement fleet in this war accidentally fired on British trawlers in the Dogger Bank incident. Togo Heihachiro won this war\u2019s Battle of Tsushima Straits. The Treaty of Portsmouth ended, for the point, what early 20th century war in which an Asian nation beat a European power?", "answer": "<b> Russo-Japanese</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this meeting of Federalists in Connecticut.", "answer": "<b> Hartford Convention</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Twenty of these units were employed at the Battle of Heraclea by Pyrrhus of Epirus. These units were forced to scatter after Metellus\u2019 troops used javelins from a ditch at the Battle of Panormus. During his triumph attempt, Pompey was unsuccessful in attempting to enter the gates of Rome with four of these units. Though some were able to be used during the Second Punic War, many of these units perished during the crossing of the Alps. For the point, name these animal units that could pierce soldiers with their tusks.", "answer": "war<b> elephant</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, Daniel Owino Misiani and other musicians blended Congolese soukous [soo-koo] and South African<em> kwela</em> music into a genre called benga. In 1976, a university in this country fired imprisoned professor and author of<em> A Grain of Wheat</em>, Ngugi wa Thiongo. The neighborhood of Kasarani is home to a stadium named for this country\u2019s second president, Daniel arap Moi [moh-ee]. Bronislaw Malinowski wrote the introduction to an anthropological study of this country\u2019s Kikuyu people written by its first president. For the point, name this country where British colonial rulers moved the capital inland from Mombasa to Nairobi.", "answer": "<b> Kenya</b> Page 13", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This philosopher demonstrated the difference between imagination and intellect with the example of a chiliagon, a polygon with one thousand sides. This thinker, who supposedly experienced three visions while sleeping inside of an oven, served as an adviser to Queen Christina of Sweden. This philosopher introduced the clear and distinct ideas criterion in books like<em> Meditations on First Philosophy</em>. For the point, name this 17th century French rationalist who posited \u201ccogito ergo sum,\u201d or \u201cI think, therefore I am.\u201d", "answer": "Ren\u00b4e<b> Descartes</b> [day-kart]", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Journalist James Risen found that religious leaders who did not cooperate in this event were threatened with \u201csavage punishment\u201d by agents pretending to be communists. This event may have been inspired by the decision of the Majlis to nationalize the oil industry. Hossein Fatemi was executed and Fazlollah Zahedi rose to power following this event, which re-established the power of the Pahlavi Dynasty. The CIA planned this event as Operation Ajax. For the point, name this 1953 event that resulted in the overthrow of a democratically elected Iranian Prime Minister.", "answer": "1953<b> coup</b> d\u2019etat against Mohammad<b> Mosaddegh</b> (accept<b> Operation Ajax</b> before it is read; accept equivalent descriptions, like \u201cthe CIA<b> overthrowing Mosaddegh</b>; prompt on partial answers describing a coup, revolution, etc. in Iran that don\u2019t mention Mosaddegh)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A mayor of this city canceled the planned sale of its municipal light operations to the CEI company, sparking a 1978 default on debt payments. This city\u2019s transit system was developed by the Van Sweringen Brothers, who founded its suburb of Shaker Heights. Carl Stokes became the first African-American to be elected a mayor of an American city here, and Dennis Kucinich survived a recall election as its mayor in the 1970s. The 2016 Republican National Convention was held in, for the point, what Midwestern city that gained notoriety for the fires that burned its polluted Cuyahoga River?", "answer": "<b> Cleveland</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When this general was labeled as mad, his king replied \u201cthen I hope he will bite some of my other generals.\u201d This man\u2019s friend John Mordaunt called on him to be appointed Quartermaster General during the Raid of Rochefort, which occurred two years prior to a siege where this man fought under Jeffrey Amherst. L\u2019Anse-au-Foulon was used as a landing point at a battle where this man led a small contingent up the Saint Lawrence River. The Marquis de Montcalm was defeated by, for the point, what general who died leading his troops to victory at the Battle of Quebec?", "answer": "James<b> Wolfe</b> Page 14", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Juvenal Habyarimana\u2019s body was stored by this leader before burial by a Hindu leader. This leader\u2019s Prime Minister, Kengo wa Dondo, expelled people of Lebanese descent for trading blood diamonds. The Safari club defended this man\u2019s nation in the Shaba I conflict. This man, who built accommodations for Concorde jets at Gbadolite, his \u201cVersailles of the Jungle,\u201d killed Simba rebel leader Pierre Mulele and was overthrown by Laurent Kabila. During the Congo Crisis, this man deposed the government of Patrice Lumumba. For the point, name this long time dictator of Zaire.", "answer": "<b> Mobutu</b> Sese Seko (Kuku Ngbendu Wa Za Banga) (or Joseph-D\u00b4esir\u00b4e<b> Mobutu</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A theologian from this country founded the non-church movement in 1901. Francis Xavier was the first Catholic missionary to preach in this country, whose residents originally mistook Christianity for a new Indian religion due to its similarities with Pure Land Buddhism. In 1597, 26 Christians in this country were crucified and impaled with spears under the orders of Toyotomi Hideyoshi. For the point, name this country whose Christian population has historically been based in Nagasaki.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b> (or<b> Nihon</b>; or<b> Nippon</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This event\u2019s perpetrators wished to exact vengeance after a violent suppression of Pedro Campos\u2019revolt was described as a mere \u201cincident.\u201d The sudden arrival of Vincent Mroz helped thwart this event, whose target had been staying at the Blair House due to ongoing renovations at the White House. Oscar Collazo and Griselio Torresola, two Puerto Rican nationalists, attempted to carry out, for the point, what failed attempt on the life of the President in 1947?", "answer": "<b> attempted assassination</b> of Harry<b> Truman</b> (accept<b> shooting of Truman</b> and similar equivalents; do not accept anything that indicates Truman died)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these vehicles known as<em> R101</em> killed 48 people on its maiden voyage to Karachi. The Soci\u00b4et\u00b4e Zodiac produced the<em> SPIESS</em>, the only one of these vehicles manufactured by France. The<em> Daily Mail</em> incentivized subscribers by offering up to 200 pounds for each reader killed by one of these vehicles during World War I. The<em> Bodensee</em> and<em> Nordstern</em> were types of this vehicle built by Germany in an attempt to subvert the Treaty of Versailles. The Empire State Building\u2019s spire was intended as a mooring mast for, for the point, what type of aircraft built by Luftschiffbau Zeppelin?", "answer": "rigid<b> airship</b>s (accept<b> blimp</b>s; accept<b> Zeppelin</b>s before mentioned) Page 15", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}